"In the sweat of thy face
shalt thou eat bread...
till thou return
unto the ground,
for out of it was thou
taken, for dust thou art,
and unto dust
shalt thou return.
And Adam called
his wife's name Eve,
because she was
the mother of all living.
Wish we had eggs. Unto Adam,
also and unto his wife...
did the Lord God make coats
of skins and clothed them.
And the Lord God said, 'Behold,
I don't remember what eggs are.
the man is become as one of
us, to know good and evil,
and now, lest he put forth
his hand and also take,
and take also of the tree of
life, and eat, and live forever.'
Therefore, the Lord God sent him
forth from the Garden of Eden,
to till the ground from
whence that he was taken.
So he drove out the man and he placed
him at the east of the Garden of Eden,
cherubim and a flaming sword
which turned every way,
to keep the way
of the tree of life."
Ohh.
Step up.
William!
William.
William. William.
He managed to hightail it
in there just as fast as he could.
Figured he'd wait out
the storm.
But when he got inside,
it turned out there was a big ol'
grizzly bear sleeping in there!
Joe faced himself
a dilemma.
Sure death outside...
and sure death inside.
- Well, what did he do?
- OI'Joe, he took the quicker route.
He pulled out his gun,
he took a shot at the bear,
but it just made him mad!
She come at him, claws
a-swipin' and teeth a-snappin',
and somehow... somehow Joe
managed to get himself...
up on the back side
of the bear,
and he rolled around the
cave like a buckin' bull!
And she took his scalp
clean off...
on the roof of the cave
that day.
But you know what?
He ate her in the end.
And ever since then...
he's worn his hair long.
You know why?
No.
In deference
to the squeamish.
It was quite a fight, son.
It was quite a fight.
But there's no bears here!
Hell's full of bears, Jimmy.
But there's no bears here.
What are they
talking about?
Were you told?
Your husband didn't say?
Not this time.
They're talking about
whether to hang Stephen Meek.
Gately argued that Meek...
has taken us off track
on purpose,
that he was hired...
to get rid
of American immigrants.
So the more of us come, the more
likely the territory goes American.
It has a logic.
I suppose.
A broken one.
Mr. White wasn't swayed either.
He argued for more patience.
"We're at the man's mercy now," he said.
"Meek's just made a mistake is
all. He's just in over his head."
And then what?
We were just getting into it
again when Meek himself showed up.
He'd been hiding above us up
there in the rocks the whole time.
So that's where he was.
He strutted into the circle
with his gun in his hand.
"Well, you've found me," he said.
"Now go ahead with the killin'."
Everybody got real quiet.
It shut everybody up.
Frank Gately is happy enough to hang
a man so long as he's not around.
And?
Well, Meek got to talkin'.
Of course he did.
He says that we are
in Paiute country now.
He says that the Paiutes
are a fearsome tribe,
that they're nothing like the
Flatheads on the main stem.
If we trust him
to do his job,
well, then he welcomed
anyone to gainsay him.
Nothing about our
route. Nothing about it.
"Seen the elephant,"
my eye.
Two weeks, he said,
and we'd be in the pass.
It's been over five and we
haven't even seen a mountain yet.
What was the verdict?
We give
a few more days.
We never should have
left the main stem.
Good morning, Emily.
Morning.
Workin' like niggers
once again.
Maybe we're back
on known ground.
Oh, he was
guessing.
Everyone has
some luck sometimes.
Hyah.
Come on.
Made 10 miles today.
I'd say this is the best
shelter we've had since morning.
The wind's not gonna
be kind tonight.
It's early yet.
We won't push too hard.
I say we keep on.
The going is easy
in these parts,
and we should make the most
of this ground while we can.
Seems to be
more shelter up ahead.
Well, I'd be careful now.
This country'll
play tricks on you.
That piece you see out there
might be...
a whole lot farther
than you think.
Guarantee it.
How far
would you say?
I wouldn't say. I just know
it'll be farther than I think.
The thinness of the air makes
everything look closer than it is.
There could be water
though?
Yeah.
Possible, I reckon.
I say we keep on.
I think
I would agree.
All right.
Keep moving.
Hyah.
Come ho.
Hah.
Well, we'll have to water the
animals from our own supply tonight.
Can't go without
after a day like this.
Should've taken on more
at the river.
You need to eat. You've
been working all day.
I'm fine for now.
Please.
Evenin'.
Good evening, Mrs. Tetherow. Mr. White.
Uh, Glory, I brought
some bread to share.
That's much appreciated,
Emily.
It's my pleasure.
l- l-I have stew too,
if you'd like it.
I know you would.
No.
No, this is enough.
Thank you.
Jimmy.
It's like my feet have gloves,
like I can... I can handle
the ground that I'm walking on.
I feel the sand. I feel
the dirt. I feel the gravel.
I never slip. I never...
I don't... I never stumble.
I can follow a trail in the dark
and never stray off the path.
I live with this world. I'm
not just in it, is what I'm sayin'.
But to answer your question, Gately,
the beaver, they're played out.
That's the truth.
That market's done and gone.
There's no fortune to be had there
anymore. Your man Astor got it all.
We should have made the
trip earlier. Waited too long.
No, you know, there... there
are plenty of fortunes to be had.
I mean, the beaver, that's a... That's just
the first gift of this land. You mark my words.
Will the territory go American?
That's what I want to know.
Well, in my...
in my opinion, l...
Well, you know, it depends.
It depends on the fight...
in the Americans,
and in the English,
and in the Indians.
I'm led to believe there's 250
Americans in Oregon country.
There's seven more argonauts comin' in a
few weeks. Maybe that'll tip the scales.
Where would you
settle?
Willamette Valley.
That's where my brotherJoe
put down stakes.
Civilization
is taking hold there.
They got missionaries
in Champoeg.
Could have found God
in Virginia.
Well, if it's riches you're
after, there's riches aplenty.
The land you're headed for
is a regular second Eden.
You won't want
for riches someday.
You'll just plunge your hands
into the ground.
Come to bed.
Soon.
That was my mother's.
I know.
It's only weight now.
Jimmy!
He's gone.
I'm telling you.
He's abandoned us. He'll move
faster alone. It's what I'd do.
No, it's not
what you'd do.
He saw the writing.
How much water
you reckon?
Two days, maybe three.
Ah. He's gone by now.
He's gone by now.
There we are.
Ho!
Water! Amen.
Water ahead!
It's alkaline!
It's alkaline.
Whoa. Whoa.
Can't water here.
Not even the animals.
Well, then?
What now?
Well,
we skirt around.
Go south
till we make it around.
How far is it around?
Well, we'll find out.
Shouldn't be too far. The maps
I've seen don't record much of this.
Oh.
No.
We're not going
farther south.
Well, we can't keep
west unless you brought oars.
We're heading north.
Meet back with the
main stem if we have to.
There's scarce
grass and water up north.
South is the best bet.
Well, there's
nothing where we came from either,
and there's nothing ahead,
so I'm saying north.
We'll move closer
to the Columbia.
That way we can rejoin
the communication.
l... I see your thinking.
How many days to the
Columbia from hereabouts?
Well, too many.
West is the goal. The sooner
we get moving west, the better.
The quickest way west,
by my reckoning...
south.
Mr. Gately,
do you have an opinion?
I think north too.
Well, I'm advising against that.
Now, I've been all through
this country, more or less.
By God, you contracted me to
get you to the Valley. I will.
We understand
that, Mr. Meek. We understand.
But you work for us, Mr. Meek.
You'll be paid.
Just, uh, we're not going
around. We're going north.
Suit yourselves.
We'll do what we do.
Two shots if we find water.
Hyah!
Mrs. Tetherow, look what we found!
What is it, Emily?
Jimmy.
So he wore clothes?
Yes.
Yes, some.
Paint on his face?
No.
Horse?
Uh, yes.
Was he carryin' a weapon?
A knife or a bow?
Uh... no.
No, I don't think so.
I'm not sure. I was upset.
He-He had a... a scar
on his shoulder though.
Well, if he wore clothes,
he's no Digger.
They're hardly
more than animals.
We're too far south for
that anyway. Might be Paiute.
Could be Nez Perce.
He could be Cayuse.
They're from the north.
It's far west for Blackfoot,
but that's possible.
And what does that mean?
Jimmy,
go help your mother.
Well, frankly, I'm amazed.
Mrs. Tetherow saw this redskin
and lived to tell the tale.
I mean, you rarely see
hide nor hair of a hostile...
till he just jumps you
and cuts your throat.
They can disappear
in their own shadow.
They can hide under a wolf skin so
quiet, you step on 'em before you know it.
And where one redskin is, there's
a dozen more just lurkin' nearby.
And they're all armed by now.
And sometimes...
I mean, sometimes they wait till they're
fired on, but most often they don't.
When they come
on a woman,
they kill her.
I mean, they'd never dream
of sparin' a woman.
So I'm guessin'
it's Cayuse.
On a horse
this far north.
I mean, they roam all over the basin
here, all the way down to Mexico.
They pick up slaves from the
Klamaths. They sell' em at Celilo.
We'll find out presently,
I reckon.
No fires tonight.
And double watch.
Dandy.
Mercy.
Hell's full of
Indians, my friends.
You were lucky tonight,
ma'am.
Don't want a blanket.
Don't make it worse.
Cold is the least
of my troubles.
Hmm.
It's only a few days north to
the Columbia by my reckoning.
I been keepin' notes.
What if we don't find
water soon? We will.
Your optimism.
I'm sorry.
Is he ignorant,
or is he
just plain evil?
That's my quandary.
It's impossible to know.
We can't know.
That's very comforting,
Mr. Tetherow.
Well,
we made our decision.
This is all gonna be
a bad dream soon.
It's gonna be
a story to tell.
I don't blame him
for not knowing.
I blame him
for saying he did.
That fool.
Solomon?
Dry breakfast?
No.
Might as well eat the dust.
Ladies.
Fine morning.
I'd like to know how.
Well, not too hot. Plus smooth
ground. Could be a piece worse.
It's not today
that's weighing on me.
We'll follow
the land downhill.
The water's more likely in the lower places.
That's fine.
Heed. Stay with us.
Broken axle.
I'm gonna bring this
wheel off. All right.
Are those our mountains, Mr. Meek?
Oh, no. No, no.
We'll know
our mountains, Jimmy.
Hell's full of mountains.
Those aren't them.
What are they?
Well, they...
They're nameless,
I suppose.
We'll call 'em Jimmy's Mountains.
What do you say to that?
I suppose so.
Mm-hmm.
Jimmy's Mountains.
We get to
the Willamette Valley,
I'll tell
the cartographers.
We'll print it on the map.
Hmm?
I don't know, Mr. Meek.
You never womaned, Mr. Meek?
Indeed I have.
Numerous times.
Squaws in these parts start lookin'
mighty white after 20 years' time.
Oh, dear.
Sometimes I get the sense you don't
care for me much, Mrs. Tetherow.
Oh, I have no feelings
one way or the other, Mr. Meek.
That's... That's just a
kind way of saying you don't like me.
I don't like where we are.
So, that's what you think,
that we're lost?
I'd say that seems about the
right word for it. We're not lost.
We're not lost.
We're just finding our way.
I certainly hope so.
We gonna make all right.
Oh, you don't need to
patronize me, Mr. Meek.
Well, now I think
you're flirtin' with me, ma'am.
You don't know much about
women, do you, Stephen Meek?
Why, l-I know...
somethin' or other.
If you say so.
Well, I know women are different
from men. I know that much.
I'll tell you the difference,
if you care to hear it.
I don't doubt you will.
Women...
Women are created
on the principle of chaos...
the chaos of creation, disorder,
bringin' new things into the world.
Men are created on the
principle of destruction.
It's like cleansing,
ordering destruction.
You think I'm wrong,
you can tell me.
Chaos and destruction. Those
two genders are always at it.
Chaos and destruction.
Well, I don't know.
I have to think about it.
Mm-hmm.
Jimmy, I told you not to wander.
I wasn't wandering, Ma. Jimmy!
- Ma, l...
- You were wandering.
If you wander again,
your father will tan you.
You found this?
Just down the
gully. There's lots.
More? How much more?
Enough to fill this bucket
more times than I can count.
Jimmy, you
know about exaggerating.
It's the neighbor
to a lie.
Look.
Hmm.
Here.
It's real, all right.
VáIgame Dios.
The Lord has his plan,
I'd say.
Brought us here
by dark design.
Mm-hmm.
Well,
let's get this done.
You can't drink gold.
Some timing.
Am I right in understandin'...
that you and Mrs. Tetherow
was recently hitched?
That's right.
Took you a while to get
settled down, I'd say.
Must have grown
accustomed to your freedom.
I was settled before.
She passed away.
I'm sorry to hear that.
You're a lucky man though.
Found yourself
a nice, young woman...
Jimmy, where are you?
Jimmy! Where are you?
Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa.
I saw him! I saw the Indian! Jimmy.
The one with the scar!
Where? Which way, exactly?
That-a-way, Mr.
Meek. How far gone?
Not a quarter-mile.
And he saw you?
Oh, yes.
Good boy.
Jimmy! Come here!
You mustn't wander off.
Keep on this path north.
I'll be back when I got him.
Wait.
Solomon!
I'll be back.
Please!
I'll be back!
Well, you heard them.
We'll keep moving.
They haven't been long.
It's not been long, Henley.
What's wrong, Sylvie?
Come here.
"Behold, him that keepeth Israel
shall neither slumber nor sleep.
The Lord is thy keeper. The Lord
is thy shade upon thy right hand.
The sun shall not
smite thee."
"The Lord is thy keeper. The Lord
is thy shade upon thy right hand.
The sun
shall not smite thee."
He's a quick one.
Might have gotten away if it
hadn't been for Meek's eye.
Horse got away
though.
Now, I know my word isn't
worth much in these parts,
but in this case I'm just as
sure as sundown we kill him now.
What do you think, Solomon?
You brought him
for a reason.
He's from these parts.
He's healthy.
He knows where the water is.
That's my reasoning.
He's barely clothed.
He'd just as soon die with us.
They don't think
of life the way we do.
That's documented fact.
I think we need him.
I don't like it,
but I see your logic.
Oh, my, don't this beat all.
You know what I've seen
his heathen's brothers do?
Strip the flesh clean off a
man while he's still breathin'.
I've seen 'em
cut a man's eyelids off...
and bury him
in the sand...
and leave him
just starin' at the sun.
You can feed 'em. You can treat 'em
to the best fixings in your lodge.
They'll turn around... Boom!
Steal your horses.
We've come to
a terrible place.
What do you think?
We need water.
That much I know.
Yeah. I don't see
any other way.
Can't say I do either.
Well, let's take a vote.
Who says we keep him?
Aye.
Got some pumpkins.
How do we get our meaning
across? Hell if I know.
Water.
Where's water?
Do you know water?
He doesn't know
the word "water."
Where's water?
Here. Drink. Drink.
Water?
He doesn't understand.
You know the word "water,"
you dumb son of a bitch!
That's right, you mongrel.
Mr. Meek!
Get away.
You have no idea
what you're dealing with.
It ain't Main Street.
It ain't
the village green.
Please.
Here.
Yours.
One now, for you.
One later.
Water. Us?
Blanket.
You.
Understand?
That there is the law
of the land, Mr. Meek.
Barter.
Evening. Evening.
I'll take
first watch.
That's fine.
Dandy.
Excuse me.
Blue Mountains
out that way, eventually.
His country.
About what you'd expect.
He's a killer, ma'am.
Don't get too close.
What?
Well, everything the steers
have is one less thing for us.
Mr. Tetherow?
Yes, ma'am.
How much further
by your calculation?
Well, it's hard to say,
you know.
It's doubtful it's more than
a day's journey from here.
The Indian, he wasn't carrying
anything, so he can't have come far.
So we'll find water today.
It would be a day alone.
For us, it could be today.
It could be tomorrow.
What are you doing, Emily?
I'm going to fix his boot.
You shouldn't.
Well, I don't like it
any more than you do.
But I want him
to owe me something.
It's a pin.
For sewing.
That's nothing.
You can't even imagine
what we've done.
The cities we've built.
Oh, God, the stench.
Hold on. Let me finish.
There.
How far
do we have to go?
How far do we have to go?
How long?
A man-child.
How's your friend?
Wha...
About the same
as the rest of us, I'd say.
Thirsty, hungry.
I was just onto telling
Mr. Gately here about the time...
I surprised
a band of Blackfeet...
down by the headwaters
of the Missouri.
It was quite a day.
See, our group was armed,
and theirs wasn't.
We pulled up, and they
all just dove into the water.
We lay there on the bank...
and shot 'em
when they come up for air.
Passed the whole afternoon
that way.
Just ducking
and diving and shooting.
It was a good ol' time.
Is this meant to bring me
over to something? No, ma'am.
And I don't excuse
what we did there that day.
You know, playing games
with those men's lives.
I don't paint myself
as anything but a sinner.
But your friend there...
He's worse than a sinner 'cause
he don't even know he's sinning.
It's the Cayuse we're talking
about... "The People of the Stones."
Even Indians despise these Indians.
They're slave traders. They're
welchers. It's even worse.
Well, you could go your
own way anytime, Mr. Meek.
Stephen Meek
does not shirk a fight.
If there's blood to be shed,
I'll be there.
I'll put in my share.
Vanity.
That's all I see.
# Nearer to Thee #
# Even though it be a cross #
#That raiseth me #
# Still, all my song shall be #
# Nearer, my God, to Thee #
# Nearer to Thee #
#Though
like the wanderer ##
Millie, stay back.
Mr. Gately.
Mr. Gately, what is it?
William... Mr.
White, give me a hand.
Here. Here.
Oh, my God,
I knew it.
Okay.
Oh. Look at this.
Here. This is what Millie
saw him leaving behind earlier.
She saw
this tonight and she came out.
What is it?
We caught him signaling to
someone, leaving word behind.
I caught him myself.
Look at this. Look at this.
It means something. He's been
making them every step of the way.
- What does it mean?
- Hell if I know.
But it means something
to somebody.
It's a
message. Just look at it.
This is nothing. This is religion.
It's how they pray to their gods.
No, it's a signal.
They're out there
looking for him, his kin,
and he's leading them
right along.
Open your eyes, Solomon. God
knows where he's taking us.
He's been walking up the ridges
as if he's looking for someone.
Finally, they're coming
around. After all we've done?
God knows what mischief
he's made already.
Millie, quiet down.
Let's hang him from
the wagon tongues tonight.
It's better late than never.
That's a message. No.
This is nothing.
There's no one out there.
They'd have
made themselves known by now.
Go back to bed.
This will all look different
in the light of day.
It's on your head, Solomon.
That's fine.
Give it another day.
Well, we'll get that blanket of
yours back one way or another, friend.
Come ha. Come ha.
Come ha.
It's a sign!
A sign! A sign!
Calm down, Millie.
They made it.
They're giving him orders! It's nothing.
You'll see.
Step up.
We'll all see. Come on. Calm down.
Step up!
Please, Thomas.
Step up.
Please, I wanna go home.
I wanna go home. Step up.
Whoa! Whoa!
What's he saying?
Well, who knows?
He's saying we're close.
He's saying...
He's saying, "Just over
the hill. Just over there."
It's a steep grade.
Can the wagons make it?
I don't see much choice.
Well, someone
could go on ahead.
It can't be far now.
They could come back
and let us know what's ahead.
No. We're together.
We're... We're all
in this the same.
Yeah, up to our necks.
We can make it all right.
Just go one wagon at a time.
Tighten up.
Don't put yourself out, boy.
Go find some shade. We'll
come find you when we're done.
All right.
Get back up.
Ma, make some room
in the wagon.
We'll be needing to take on
some weight. We'll make room too.
That's mighty white of
you. This was his plan all along.
It's just what he wanted.
Millie, calm down, please.
They're coming.
They're almost here!
Millie, calm down.
We'll make the crossing,
and on the other side,
we'll start fresh.
All you need is your...
All you need
is your strong back.
What's in this?
Yeah, we use that.
Hey! Hey! Put that down!
That don't belong to you!
Have some respect!
Hey! I said
put that down, heathen!
I'm warning you. If you don't put that down
right now, you're gonna be mighty sorry.
What does it matter? Just let him be.
Well, it's the principle
of the matter.
All right, that's it.
That's it.
You've taken us just about
as far as you need to go.
End this game right now.
Put it away, Meek.
There's no need.
Oh, I see a need.
Well, you... so you got
some feeling in you after all.
I'd be wary.
You people got no idea what
you're dealing with here.
Well, neither do you, Mr. Meek.
You've proved that amply by now.
It seems like your woman got some
Indian blood in her, Mr. Tetherow.
She's got something, all right.
Yeah, you think this
heathen's as good as his word.
You got no idea what he's
fixing to do. It could be...
Who knows
what's over that hill?
Could be water.
Could be an army
of heathens.
Could be.
Well, maybe you'd
like to wager.
Water or blood.
I'll leave the wagering
to men like you.
Don't think
you ain't wagering.
And you don't even know
what cards you got.
That's some pumpkins.
You a lucky savage, boy.
You got
a guardian angel here.
All in good time.
All in good time
the cards are gonna fall.
They're gonna fall real soon.
Thank you.
Heavenly Father,
we thank you for this food...
and for the many mercies
you have blessed us with.
We ask that you continue to
protect us on our journey...
and guide us
as it is thy will.
In Christ's name. Amen.
Amen. Amen.
I'm just thinking of
my father's pigs back home.
All safe and warm
in their pens.
Emily.
Oh, William, thank you.
What do you see out there?
Hard to say.
No, there's no saying,
is there?
Do you think
he's trustworthy?
The Indian?
I can't... say as I do.
I trust you is all.
But you're putting
your trust in him.
You're doubtful.
I have my doubts.
What are you thinking,
Solomon?
l...
I just hope Meek hasn't
twisted you up, is all.
Whoa! Whoa!
Whoa, whoa!
Whoa!
He won't drink. I've tried
every day, but he refuses.
Emily,
I don't know what to do.
Please. Please.
My darling, I know.
I know.
I know,
I know, I know.
I know.
We're close, friend.
Stay with us.
You stay with us.
Please, please drink,
my darling. Please.
Please, William.
Drink some more.
Mrs. White, we're gonna have to
make some more room in the wagon.
Of course.
Jimmy,
stay with your father.
Oh, William.
Drink. There you go.
Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa!
Whoa! Whoa!
Mama, a tree can't
live without water. Can it?
Thomas, we can still go
back. We can try for the Columbia.
Millie, we're close.
That's just it. We're
close, but we don't know what to.
We've been through
this. We don't know, either way.
Thomas, please.
We still have a choice.
What about you, Mrs. White?
Which way
does your family prefer?
We stay the course.
We don't have a choice,
not that I see.
Meek?
I'm taking my orders
from you now, Mr. Tetherow,
Mrs. Tetherow.
And we're all taking
our orders from him, I'd say.
We're all just
playing our parts now.
This was written
long before we got here.
I'm at your command.